Guide to the Chocolate Bayou Theater Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Chocolate Bayou Theater Collection
1979-1987
08/2007-026
Chocolate Bayou Theater Company
3.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Chocolate Bayou Theater Company Collection consists of 3 boxes of materials dating from 1979-1988. The collection is divided into two series: Administrative Papers and Productions.
Historical Note:
The Chocolate Bayou Theater Company’s origins date back to 1973 when Leonard Wagner established a semi-professional community theater in conjunction with Alvin Community College. When the college suspended its theater program, Wagner decided to transform the group into a non-profit professional theater in collaboration with Pat Miller. Their mission was to produce high quality, intimate professional theater while developing playwrights and a company of actors. Together they moved the Chocolate Bayou Theater Company to a new location a few miles north to Houston.
Chocolate Bayou established a reputation mounting new plays and supporting new playwrights through their Preston Jones New Play Symposium. The symposium was named for the playwright Preston Jones who donated his new play to CBTC for their first production. Jones, a close friend of Miller and Wagner, died two weeks before the play was produced.
Financial difficulties forced the company to close in 1987. Chocolate Bayou was enjoying critical and popular success but faced outstanding debts and the economic downturn in Houston. In its final year CBTC produced seven premieres of new plays. Attempts were made to revive CBTC but were unsuccessful. The company mounted more than 100 productions and received two Rockefeller Foundation grants.
Sources:
Dauphin, Sue. Houston by Stages: A History of Theatre in Houston.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Chocolate Bayou Theater Company
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); Negatives (photographic); Photographs; Slides; Theater programs
Topical Term:
Performing arts; Theater
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The Chocolate Bayou Theater Company Collection consists of 3 boxes of materials dating from 1979-1988. The collection is divided into two series: Administrative Papers and Productions.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative Papers
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series include correspondence, photographs, financial and reorganization plans. Clippings, correspondence, and meeting minutes concerning the closure of CBTC are grouped together. Also included are photographs, clippings, and programs pertaining to the Preston Jones New Playwright Symposium named in honor of playwright, collaborator and close friend, Preston Jones.
  - Clippings
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Closure
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minutes-Board of Trustees (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Revival attempts and legal issues (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence
    - Blessing, Lee (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gallagher, Mary (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hermann, Edward (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Johns, Andrew (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jones, Mary Sue (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jones, Thomas Cadawallader (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Nadel, Norman (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Press, Toni (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Rogers, Art (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Walz, Mark (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Wise, William (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Wylie, Stephen (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - First name only (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fundraising
    - Campaigns (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs
    - Co-directors: Pat Miller and Leonard Wagner, building (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Predecessor, Alvin Community College (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Preston Jones + Preston Jones New Playwright Symposium
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fliers (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Preston Jones Memorials (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Program (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Publications
    - Financial Report, 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Fliers (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Operational Request, 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Season Subscriptions (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1984-85 Season (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Productions, 1979-1987
  Clippings, photographs, and programs of Chocolate Bayou Theater productions organized alphabetically by production title.
  - 84, Charing Cross Road
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Photograph (Ovs box 1, Item 1)
  - The Adventure of the Speckled Band
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - An American Fable
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Angry Housewives
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Beauty and the Beast
    - Negatives (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bertha, the Beautiful Typewriter Girl
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Candida
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Count Dracula
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dangerous Corner
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Deep in the Heart
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Premiere Gala (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Do It by the Book
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Photograph (Ovs box 1, Item 2)
  - Doctors and Diseases
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dogg's Hamlet
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dorian
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Educating Rita
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - A Flea in her Ear
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Foxfire
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gemini
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - The Gift of the Magi
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Gone to Texas
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Harvey
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Hedda Gabler
    - Photograph (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Hothouse
    - Clipping (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Kringle's Window
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Land of Fire
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The Last Meeting of the Knights of the White Magnolia
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Luna Vista
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Luv
    - Clipping (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Man with a Raincoat
    - Clipping (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Master Harold
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - A Moon for the Misbegotten
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Photograph (Ovs box 1, Item 3)
  - Murder at the Vicarage
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Nice People Dancing...
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Night & Day
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Of Mice and Men
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Photograph (Ovs box 1, Item 4)
  - Otherwise Engaged
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Pigeons on the Walk
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Plenty
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Photograph (Ovs box 1, Item 5)
  - The Pony Ring
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Prufrock's Montage
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Relatively Speaking
    - Programs (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Remember
    - (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Rookery Nook
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Rude Times
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Santa Fe Sunshine
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Scheherazade
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Skirmishes
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Slow Dance on the Killing Ground
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Stage Struck
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - A Taste of Honey
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - To Gillian on her 37th Birthday
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - We Won't Pay! We Won't Pay!
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Programs (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Win/Lose/Draw
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - The Woolgatherers
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Years in the Making
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Program (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Zastrozzi
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Various/Miscellaneous Productions
    - Negatives (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Slides (Box 2, Folder 104)